Blazer Family papers, 1857-1966 (bulk 1870-1955)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Blazer Family papers, 1857-1966 (bulk 1870-1955)
MS 034
Blazer family
Chiefly photocopies of correspondence, manuscripts, land claims, patents, machinery catalogs, and legal papers of Armer Newton Blazer; also photocopied correspondence and manuscripts of Paul Blazer, and photograph reprints.
1.6 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Dr. Joseph Hoy Blazer was a New Mexican pioneer, dentist, merchant, and sawmill owner on the Tularosa River, within what became the Mescalero Apache Indian Reservation. Blazers's daughter Emma married Dr. John Howard Thompson, a physician on the Mescalero Reservation, then in El Paso, Texas. Blazer's son Armer carried on the mill business, while designing mechanical inventions and writing on local history. Armer's son, Paul, also researched local history and collected historic photographs.
Organization
This collection is organized into four series.
Series I: Blazer family materials, 1857-1966
Series II: A.N. Blazer: Correspondence & Inventions, 1897-1962
Series III: A.N. Blazer manuscripts, 1928-1939
Series IV: Paul Blazer Photographs, 1919-1965
Scope and Content Note
Chiefly photocopies of correspondence, manuscripts, land claims, patents, machinery catalogs, and legal papers of Armer Newton Blazer; also photocopied correspondence and manuscripts of Paul Blazer, and photograph reprints. One of Armer's correspondents is the western artist and writer William R. Leigh; the letters concern historical details for his book Littlefoot, and include his art exhibition brochures. Designs for Armer's inventions illustrate and describe the Blazer Internal-Combustion Rotary Engine, 1898; the Blazer Power Wheel, 1898; and the Blazer Deep- Well Pump, 1910. His manuscripts on historic topics are titled "Santana" and "Los Jirones." Also present are Dr. Howard Thompson's manuscript "Makers of El Paso," and Paul Blazer's "History of Tularosa."
Photographs include Blazer family members; the mill and homestead; views of the reservation, depicting Mescalero Indians, their homes, agency buildings and employees; and other individuals, families, and social groups in the Mescalero area. Most of the origianl images dated from 1870 to 1914. Miscellaneous documents include some of J.H.Blazer's business correspondence, and legal papers regarding stolen cattle and a shoot-out at Blazer's Mill. Also, Emma Thompson's 1900 diary of Mexico and 1908 diary of Europe. Among materials on New Mexico is William V. Morrison's file of newspapers articles and correspondence about Billy the Kid; newspaper articles about Lincoln County pioneers; and a Mescalero vocabulary, as given by Percy Bigmouth in 1932.
Original materials are in the possession of the Blazer family.
Billy, the Kid; Blazer, Joseph Hoy, 1828-1898; Leigh, William Robinson, 1866-1955; Thompson, Emma -- Diaries; Thompson, John Howard, 1851-1930; United States. -- Bureau of Indian Affairs. -- Mescalero Agency; Blazer's Mill (N.M.); Pioneers -- New Mexico; Pioneers -- Texas; Frontier and pioneer life -- New Mexico; Apache Indians -- History; Mescalero language -- Dictionaries -- English; English language -- Dictionaries -- Mescalero; Indian reservations -- New Mexico -- History; Lincoln County War, 1878; Otero County (N.M.) -- History; Lincoln County (N.M.) -- History; Mescalero Indian Reservation (N.M.) -- History -- 19th century; El Paso (Tex.) -- History; Tularosa (N.M.) -- History; Correspondence; Diaries; Photographs; Manuscripts; Articles; Land Claims
Related Material
Financial records of Blazer's Mill, 1871-1908, and photographs available on Microfilm 1572.
Container List
- Series I: Blazer family materials, 1857-1966
  - Biographical material (Includes biographical sketches of various members of the faily, records of births and deaths, clippings, etc.). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Allen Family Correspondence. 1857, 1861-1863, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Joseph H. Blazer Correspondence and Miscellaneous Papers. 1868-1876 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Land Claim (Legal Papers, Correspondence, etc.). 1864-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
  - Dr. Howard Thompson: Makers of El Paso (Ms.)., No Date (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Emma (Blazer) Thompson: Diaries, (Includes trips to Mexico and Europe). 1900-1901, 1904, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - William V. Morrison: Correspondence about Billy the Kid, (Includes clippings, articles, etc.). 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lincoln County Pioneers (Various clippings, articles, etc.)., No Date (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: A.N. Blazer: Correspondence and Inventions, 1897-1962
  - Correspondence, etc. (Family). 1900-1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, etc. (Tularosa Community Ditch). 1906-1909, 1934-1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, etc. (Highway Right-of-way). 1924-1940 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, etc. (William R. Leigh). 1931-1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, etc. (Miscellaneous). 1925-1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, etc. (inventions: Spiral Pump and Gasoline Engine). 1919-1921 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, etc. (Inventions: Various). 1897-1912, 1938-1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Patents (by A.N. Blazer and other)., No Date (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Machinery (Catalogs, brochures, etc.)., No Date (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Records etc., No Date (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series III: A.N. Blazer: Manuscripts, 1928-1939
  - Correspondence regarding Manuscripts. 1928-1939 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - A.N. Blazer: Los Jirones (Ms.)., No Date (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - A.N. Blazer: Santana (Ms.)., No Date (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - A.N. Blazer: Miscellaneous Articles (Ms. and clippings)., No Date (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Varous Notes, etc., on Mescalero Apaches., No Date (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mescalero Vocabulary., No Date (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Paul Blazer Photographs, 1919-1965
  - Photographs: Blazer Family., No Date (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photographs: Blazer's Mill., No Date (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photographs: Individuals (Includes Reservation Agency personnel)., No Date (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs: Group Pictures (Includes Reservation Agency personnel, school children, varous activities on the Reservation, etc.)., No Date (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photographs: Mescalero Indian Reservation and Agency (Buildings, Indian groups, land)., No Date (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photographs: Indians (Individual and group pictures of various Apache tribes; also some of Hopi and Zuni Indians)., No Date (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photographs: Places (Ft. Stanton, Bent's Mine, Hotel at Elk SPrings, White Oaks, etc.)., No Date (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Paul Blazer: Correspondence (Miscellaneous). 1919-1965 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Paul Blazer: Correspondence (Family). 1949-1965 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Paul Blazer: Articles, notes, etc., No Date (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Mescalero Indian Cattle Growers Assoc. (Reports). 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)